said welcome back and today we are going
to see how to do consumer setup. So see
this looks very small topic like
consumer setup, right? All we have to do
is that.
But when I will start you will see like
how many subtopics we can have in this
one. Okay? So let's start without any
wasting time.
So if you're already following this
series in the Kafka architecture topic
I have shown you the complete consumer
read flow.
Okay? So these are all the 13 step in
which consumer
flow works.
Okay?
So I will take just 5 minutes to quickly
go through it. But if you have any doubt
in this flow, I would highly recommend
kindly check out the architecture topic
in which I have gone through this in
deep and slowly. Okay?
But
before we start or jump to the setup
let's
have a quick recap of this flow.
So in a step one we
setting up a consumer like which group
it want to join and which topic it want
to read. Okay? Step two is like okay,
the group
based on this group ID it compute the
partition. You know that internally
Kafka maintain \underscore} consumer
\underscore} offsets topic which has 50
partition.
Okay? Now let's say broker one, broker
two, two brokers are there. So this
topic 50 partition let's say one to 25
partition is hold by broker one
and 26 to remaining 50 let's say hold by
broker two.
So for partition number one to partition
number 25 broker one you can say that is
the group coordinator.
And for partition number 26 to 25 broker
two is the leader and it is considered
as a group coordinator.
You can say that.
Okay? So now in the step two
I have like a This is a group I want to
join, notification service.
I do that hash of notification service
group ID mod 50 because total 50
partition, I got 23. So, now let's say
this 23 belongs to this broker one.
Okay? 23 partition, who is the leader?
Broker one. So, who is the group
coordinator for this group uh consumer
group notification service? Broker one
is the group coordinator. Okay?
So, step two is just to find out the
partition.
Where the
like which broker
is going to manage this group.
Now, in the step three, what it does is
it hit any broker, any broker, and find
out the metadata information. Like
metadata information about like
first _consumer_offset
partition zero, who is the leader?
Leader, let's say broker one. Partition
one, who is the leader? Let's say
partition 50, who is the leader?
Okay? Like this, it find out a
metadata. Also
topic like of Let's say order.
Uh _events. This is the topic. It's
partition zero, who is the leader?
It's partition one, who is the leader?
So, all this metadata information it
fetch out.
After that, what it will do is
it will invoke the group coordinator.
So, let's say this is the partition
for this group, notification service.
The partition is 23 out of 50.
So, this 23 from this metadata consumer
offset, it know this partition 23, who
is the leader?
Let's say broker one. So, this broker
one is a group coordinator because this
broker will ultimately manage this
partition 23. Okay? So, now
this consumer will ask this broker, or
you can say that group coordinator,
"Hey, add me into this group."
Okay?
Now, what this group coordinator will
do, it will add the consumer
and also it will do rebalance. Like it
will divide the partition.
Let's say in this
notification
group which this consumer want to join.
There are already two two consumer,
consumer one consumer two.
Now, this consumer you want to add it
newly. So, means now there are three
consumer.
So,
this notification group, whatever the
topic it want to join, let's say they
want to join topic
order underscore event. This is the
topic
it want to join. So, what it will do is
it has this topic has three partition,
partition zero, partition one
and partition two.
So, earlier this three partition is
divided among these two. Let's say
partition zero, partition one is
handling by consumer one
and consumer two was handling partition
two.
Now, when you're adding a new consumer,
so rebalance has to be done.
Let's say it is handling now partition
zero, it is handling partition one, it
is handling partition two.
Okay? So, that's what it does.
Because consumer
tell, "Hey, this is a group I want to
join. This is the topic I'm interested
in."
Okay? So, it find out the metadata.
Now, from that metadata it knows that
okay, for my group information goes to
the partition 23, partition 23 leader is
broker one. It
invokes the broker one and ask that,
"Hey,
add me to this group and this is the
topic I'm interested in."
So, what group coordinator will do, it
will add the consumer into this group
and also do rebalance. Means assign a
partition for this topic.
Okay? Once it is done, this consumer
will
ask
again the group coordinator, "Okay, the
partition now let's say this
Partition two you have assigned me.
What is the offset
is already processed from where I have
to start. Okay? So, it will ask the
group coordinator.
Group coordinator will check underscore
consumer underscore offset. It has the
information that okay,
notification group,
this is the topic, this is the
partition, what is the offset
till
work is done or it has been read
successfully.
So, it will find out and it will return
the next offset which need to be
processed.
Once done,
now consumer knows that okay,
uh
for this order underscore events, I have
to taken care of partition
let's say P2 and offset which I need to
read is let's say 100.
Uh till 100 is done, so I have to read
from 101. So, now what it has to do is
it has to invoke the leader
of this topic and this partition. So, it
will check its metadata. Okay? For order
underscore event topic,
for this let's say partition two, who is
the leader? Broker.
So, it find out and it woke it and it
will ask that hey,
from 101,
return me this many bytes.
Okay? It will return, it will process
those.
Okay? And after that process, it will
commit the offset. Okay? It will update.
It will
ask the group coordinator hey, update
this info
that this group, notification let's say
group,
this topic, this partition, offset
updated let's say till 150 I am done.
Updated. Okay? Once done,
it again continue polling here. Okay?
Next, after give me
another.
Till whatever let's say 150 is done, it
again I said now give me from
to 200." Like this, it continuously go
on.
Okay? So, sorry if I am going little
faster because the same thing I have
discussed in the architecture. This is
just a
quick recap because
>> [clears throat]
>> now we are going to set up and
when we are doing the setup, everything
is configuration.
Okay? So, if you don't remember this
flow,
then the configuration is like, "Okay,
why we are doing that?" Okay?
So, now I am
hoping that with this quick flow, you
able to do
a quick recap of the whole flow what
consumer
uh might be doing internally.
Now, let's say a step one. We have
jumping into the
the actual setup.
The first thing is we have to do a
dependency at dependency in our Spring
Boot project. So, in the pom.xml, we
just have to add a spring-kafka. The
same thing which we have added for
producer. Exactly the same thing.
Okay? This bring all the dependency for
the consumer, also.
Step two. See,
what is the minimal I am showing you the
minimal configuration
is required to set up. You will see
that, "Hey, this is very, very easy.
Setting up consumer is too easy."
But,
currently we are just touching the
top of the iceberg.
Okay? There are a lot of things happen
behind. Okay?
Which I will slowly go.
Okay? But, first thing is understand
what is the minimal thing is required to
do a consumer setup. The first thing is
setting up the dependency.
Application property. This is the you
can say that the most minimalistic
important configuration which we have to
add.
Port number and the application name.
This is just uh nothing related with the
Kafka. This is just your application
name and the port on which it is
running.
So, 1 2 3 4 5, this five configuration
which you can say that very important.
The first one is bootstrap server.
Bootstrap server is why it is important?
Because
when the first fresh request you are
making, you have to fetch the metadata
information. And when you fetch the
metadata information,
like you need to at least invoke one
broker because you don't know, you don't
have metadata information yet. Okay? You
haven't restored it. So, first time you
have to invoke like producer. Similarly,
you need some entry point.
Okay? So, which broker? So, I have added
here broker one, broker two. Okay? It
will invoke any.
This is just you can say that for the
first time it will use it to fetch the
metadata information. After that, it
don't need it.
Okay? So, clear? Bootstrap.
Second is
group ID. Which consumer group your
whatever the consumer you are setting
up, which consumer group it want to
join. So, order \hyphen} consumer
\hyphen} group. This group
which my consumer wants to join. Okay?
So, this is important. You have to
provide which consumer group you have to
join.
Then we have key deserializer and value
deserializer. If you remember from the
producer setup, okay? When producer
send an event, okay?
It send
key and value, but it never send uh,
like this. It first serialize it.
Okay?
So, [snorts]
in the consumer, when it read it, it has
to deserialize it.
This key and value. The same thing. And
whatever the
you have used for the let's say key is
using uh, string serializer. Value you
have used JSON serializer.
The same thing you have to use here.
Okay?
So, let's say key deserializer I am
using is a string deserializer.
And the value deserializer I am using is
let's say JSON deserializer because in
the producer
I have used a string as a string
serializer and the value as JSON
serializer. So, here JSON deserializer.
So,
clear? 1 2 3 4. Now, last one.
Kafka consumer property is spring JSON
value default type. So, why this is
required? Whenever your value
deserializer is JSON
means what we are saying is the value
which is a JSON
we need to deserialize it into some Java
object.
But which one?
Which one I have to which one like your
consumer
convert this JSON object. Okay? So,
we have to provide one default type.
Okay?
So, spring.json.value.default.type
is here I have created one POJO
order.
Okay? So, I have provided its class path
com.eda.consumer.model.order.
This one. This class.
Okay? So, this is a default.
Okay?
I will tell you that I might not even
we have to provide this for sure. Okay?
But
you can say that
this is just a fallback.
This is just a fallback. How?
I will show you. Like why this this is
this is just for a fallback. You can say
that. At least
uh
you can say that
consumer client should at least have
one default. Okay, if I don't find
uh like which this JSON I need to
convert to an object, which one I will
use this default.
Now, you might ask that okay, apart from
this, where else it will try
to convert to a specific object, that
next I'm going to tell you.
But, this is the five minimalistic
configuration. Bootstrap server,
like
we know that why it is required.
Consumer group,
like which consumer group this consumer
need to join.
The key deserializer value deserializer
because the producer also serialize this
key and value, so we just need to
deserialize it.
Since the value [snorts] deserializer is
JSON,
so it will convert from JSON to object,
but which object uh we will I will show
you next,
but it need one default type also.
JSON, so here we have provided that
okay, if you don't find any way,
this is the default user.
Okay? And this is just POJO class I have
created in this path.
So, dependency added, the most
minimalistic application.properties
added.
Now, step three, last step, and our
consumer setup is done.
Now, here I am adding in this at the
rate component I have created order
event listener. You can create any class
name. This is just one class, and I put
at the rate component.
Now, here this is important. I have
added one Kafka listener.
Topic, the consumer which I am creating,
it want to join this group,
and it want to listen which topic? This
topic, order-events.
Okay? So, at the rate Kafka listener,
this is the topic which my consumer
wants to listen.
Okay?
Now, what any event any event which
comes from this topic, this is the
business logic which will execute.
You can say that if there are 10 event
for each event
this get executed. This code this method
get invoked.
Now here if you see
I have written this method public void
consume.
Now here this I have provided object
Java object. So now that's why I was
saying you when there is a JSON
serializer
Okay. Now what it will do is that let's
say
order
hyphen events
Okay from this one event come.
Now for this
JSON deserializer will come.
Now JSON deserializer what it will do is
it will see that okay this is the method
which need to be executed. It will see
that okay it is expecting this order. So
it will try to use this.
Okay. So this JSON deserializer in which
object it will try to deserialize this
one.
This one order.
But it's still we need to
put default is like something let's say
I have here provided payment
object. So which object this JSON
deserializer will try to convert to an
object? Let's say this payment. I have
provided payment.
Okay.
But this act as a just a fallback. Let's
say it's not able to uh you have not
provided anything here. Just assume.
But at least it
for its
>> [snorts]
>> you can say that something is mandatory
in consumer client that at least I
should know the default type.
Okay.
If I don't find any suitable uh in which
object I have to convert to this JSON
this is the default type I will use.
So that's why it is always mandatory to
provide a default type.
Okay.
So again
check this one.
So, I am writing I am writing one class
order event listener and here I have
annotated with at the rate Kafka
listener.
Which topic this Kafka will read?
Okay?
And for let's say if from this topic 10
events has come, for each event
this
method will get invoked.
Okay?
That's all.
Your consumer setup is done.
Uh on just three step. Dependency
application.property, which is like
very simple configuration.
And like
event.
Now here, let's see a demo. I know that
at this point of time so many doubts
might be coming, but let's see a demo
first.
So, let's remove everything. Again,
let's set up the cluster from a start.
So, let me remove
controller one
controller two logs
broker one logs
broker two log I have cleaned
everything.
Now, we need to generate a new
cluster ID.
Okay, got a new cluster ID. Now, let's
you know that what we have to do.
We have to add controller one,
controller two, broker one, broker two
with this cluster ID.
So, controller one added.
Controller two added.
Now, we will add
broker one
to this cluster
and broker two.
So, all four things are now attached
with one cluster ID. Now, all we have to
do is start the server. Okay. So, now
let's start over
controller one
here
and here I will start controller
two.
So, now I have a started the controller
one and controller two is also started.
Now, we will start the broker.
Now, let's start broker one
and let's start broker two. So, now
all servers are started. Our cluster is
fully set up.
Okay. And currently here we will see
let's describe the consumer events
topic. We will see there would be one
describe
uh describe. So, here if you see
currently order hyphen event do not
exist. Okay, that's expected. Now, what
we are doing is the producer
Kafka producer service, I am starting
its server.
From the producer topic, you know that
we have already have during the startup
it create this topic four partition two
replicas. Okay. Now, I'm starting the
producer.
Okay. So, producer application is
started. Now, let's again do describe
order events.
Okay.
So, 0 1 2 3. So, four partition two
replicas of each.
That is done. Order uh our cluster is
set up.
Producer is up and running.
Now, what I am doing is I am publishing
one event. Okay. Now, let's say 3
3 2 7 0 0.
This is the order ID which I am
publishing.
Okay. So,
order created and event published. So,
here order created successfully in
partition three it has gone. So
partition three.
Who is the leader of partition three?
It's leader three. Leader three is like
uh
Controller one is one, controller two
I've given ID two, and broker one.
Broker one, yes. Broker one ID is three.
So we need to check the broker one.
And uh
partition three.
Okay.
Let's check that.
And uh partition three leader is three.
So broker one we have to check. Broker
one.
Okay, broker one.
And partition three.
Order hyphen events hyphen three 00 log.
Yeah. So this is the record. 32700.
32700.
Okay.
Now, but here if you see currently our
consumer is not up. So now I am
So this is my consumer application, the
same thing which I showed you.
Like here
application.properties
12345. The five minimalistic
application.properties.
Okay. And uh
this is one listener. It is listening to
order hyphen events topic. And I'm just
printing. This is the business logic.
Receive order event this one.
So now let's start the
consumer.
I run it.
So consumer is up and running. Here if
you see that
what exactly happened? It why it didn't
consume this event? Why?
It's because it's because
the default
Now here at this point of a step where
it has asked
Hey,
give me the offset from where I have to
read.
So, currently in this
application.properties,
I haven't defined that. So, what's the
default?
When there is no offset, it's the
latest.
Okay? Whatever the latest is this, you
will get that. All the previous one,
earliest one, you won't get. Okay? So,
now
So, either one way is that we
provide it like
auto offset reset to from latest to
earliest. Okay? If you do earliest, I
will get everything.
Okay? But now, let's say our consumer is
running.
Let me publish another event, 701.
Now, this is the latest, this it will
get. So, okay? Order created an event
published. Now, let's see the consumer.
Receive order event, 01.
Why? Because
by default, it by default offset is
early latest. Okay? Not the earliest,
means from start, nothing.
So, our consumer setup is done.
So, here you can keep on producing
event. Let's say
two.
So, here you got two.
Then you put here
three.
In consumer, you got three.
Okay?
So,
this is the like minimalistic consumer
setup. Dependency,
this is the property,
and
which topic and the business logic.
Done.
Now, here if you see, hey, but you have
told so many step.
So many step.
It's all abstracted by a spring boot.
So, now let's go one level deeper
because we don't like this level of
abstraction.
We want something more.
Okay?
Now, let's go one level deeper and see
what we can understand.
So, I'm whatever the code I'm showing
you, that's let's say conceptual which I
believe this what might a SpringBoot
doing internally.
Okay?
So,
let's say we are not using SpringBoot at
all.
So, we have one Kafka consumer. So,
within a
uh within you can say that the uh
Kafka consumer library,
there is a class Kafka consumer.
So, it's this is the main consumer which
we have to create.
So, internally what a SpringBoot might
be doing is it's creating a new object
of Kafka consumer. And if you go to this
Kafka consumer class, it accept a
properties. This is nothing but a map.
So, in this properties,
whatever then application.properties we
add for consumer Kafka Kafka consumer,
that generally get added here. Okay?
Now, let's say we are not using a
SpringBoot. So, first thing it might be
doing is creating all this property and
inside this property we have to provide
everything bootstrap server group ID key
deserializer value deserializer etc.
etc. etc.
Okay?
Now, it will create a new Kafka consumer
object new Kafka consumer and
the argument it accept is this
property. Okay? So, our Kafka consumer
object is created
at this point of time.
Now, this consumer
wants to join this group, but which
topic it want to subscribe is so there
is a method called consumer.subscribe.
And you know that one consumer
can subscribe so many topics. Okay? So,
that's why it has a list. If you go
inside this Kafka consumer, you will
find the subscribe and which is an
array. So, currently let's say I want to
subscribe only one topic.
So, arrays.add list order-events. So,
currently till now I have done this that
okay
uh I have created a consumer through
this properties
>> [snorts]
>> and I've also tell which event or which
topic I want to listen. Done.
Now, after that what it might be doing
it might be
connecting one of the broker and fetch
the cluster metadata information.
Okay? Using this uh bootstrap server, it
connect with one of the cluster broker
and fetch the metadata info.
Done.
Now, this is the important loop. It
while true
continuously now it work.
Now, what it will do is this consumer,
what it will do is it will do
continuously poll.
And internally if you go inside this
poll method, this is the main thing it
does. Like all here if you see that
majority of task which is happening
inside the poll itself.
So, if it is the first call, first call.
Okay? What it will do? It will send the
join group request, join group request
to group coordinator. Hey,
add me to this group.
Okay?
What it will receive? It will receive
the partition assignment. What it uh
group coordinator will ultimately will
do is group coordinator ultimately will
add the consumer into the group and also
the partition it want to subscribe from
that partition, it will get one
assignment that hey, you are now
uh dealing with this partition of the
topic which you are subscribed. So, it
get the partition assignment.
Now, internally it will do request the
last committed offset. Okay? For this
partition which you have assigned, what
is the last committed offset? Now,
everything is happening within poll
internally. It's all abstracted with us.
Okay? So, group coordinator will check
the consumer offset
and find out that, okay, for this
partition, this topic, this partition,
this group,
what is the last offset processed? Okay,
it will return that.
And after that, once it knows, it will
send the fetch request to the partition
leader. This is step it will do.
Okay?
After that, it will send to the order
hyphen event, let's say partition it is
assigned to. So, it will call the
broker,
leader broker of this partition two of
the order event. And the offset it knows
that, hey, I want to read from this
offset.
So,
everything happens in the first call.
Now, in the subsequent call, it don't
have to add into the group coordinator
again, partition assignment, or
everything is done. For the subsequent
call, what it will do is it will just
send the fetch request
for the new data continuously, like the
same thing.
For continue polling and move to step
it. It will just keep calling the
broker, hey, now return me next 50 data,
next 50, next 50. Okay? All this group
coordinator thing is all done.
So, that's done.
So, now let's say you got the records
from the poll, you got the records.
Let's say you got 50 records.
Now, there is a concept called auto
commit.
Okay? If you remember, I have told you
in this consumer we have auto commit. In
the auto commit, let's say
we have tell that after every 5 second,
auto commit should have happened. So,
after 5 second means it will check
everything in the while loop only.
If auto commit enabled, yes,
and commit interval passed, it check
that, yes, 5 second has been passed,
let's say.
Then it will commit. So, I If you
remember again from the architecture,
there is one problem. Say, you have
fetch 50 records.
Okay? Let's say you have fetch from 100
to 150. This record you have fetch.
But, now you have commit the offset.
Hey, so what offset in the
group coordinator you are sending? That,
hey, for this group,
this topic, this partition, my offset is
150.
You are saying that, hey, till 150 I'm
done. But, still you haven't processed
it. It just auto commit.
If something crash will happen, and you
will restart again, do poll again,
in the from the group offset, what you
will find? Okay, if till 150 are done,
you have to start from 151. So, you lost
some data.
Okay? So, that's why in production, auto
commit never used.
That's just my experience.
Okay?
So, that is where auto commit, I
believe, should be
uh reside in the code. Again, this is a
conceptual code. This is not something
because framework code, if you go, it's
too huge and too complicate. This is my
understanding what
uh Spring Boot might be doing
internally.
Okay?
After that, auto commit done, there is
like whatever the records you got, 50
records, it iterate over for loop. For
each record, one by one, it run the
business logic.
Okay? After that,
once it is done the s-
complete batch, you can say that of the
50 batch,
now let's say if auto commit is false,
we have to manually do the commit sync.
Okay? So, the for manual, there are two
option, commit sync, commit async.
Commit sync means block until broker
confirm
that, yes,
it is properly written, consumer
underscore offset properly updated. In
commit async, it's fire and forget. I
don't
bother about the broker acknowledgement
that whether it is
able to commit offset properly or not.
So, we have to use one of them.
Okay, and continuously again while true,
again it will do poll. So, it's
continuously poll.
Okay, and anytime
any this loop breaks means your consumer
is dead. It will leave the consumer
group.
Okay, and when it leave the consumer
group, no heartbeat sent by consumer
because there is a background thread
also running by the consumer. So, your
consumer you have a broker
and let's say this is a group
coordinator.
So, this consumer there is a background
thread which every sometime send the
heartbeat. Hey, I am alive. I am alive.
I am alive.
Now, let's say when this consumer leave
this group, you can say that it is dead
or crashed something.
It won't send this heartbeat.
Okay, if it won't send the heartbeat,
the group coordinator will say that
okay, this consumer might have
like crash or something, then the
rebalance will start.
We'll see that later.
But for now, understand
over three steps what we have done.
Spring Boot does a lot of abstraction.
Internally might be happening all of
this thing.
So,
good thing is
again,
let's say even if you understand this
framework, we don't have to write all of
this.
Okay, so here if you see the same code,
all these properties
is now
written into application.properties.
Okay, there are so many configurations.
I will try to cover as many important
configurations. Okay,
I have started with this five important
one which is very much required. Uh for
other rest, default is present.
Okay,
but this
you can say that this 1 2
4, 5. This five is must. Rest everything
default is present.
So,
from this conceptual framework code,
this property is you can say that we can
we don't have to write this.
If you put into application.properties,
the framework automatically read this
application.properties
and create this map for us.
So, this is handled.
All we So, this is we have All we have
to write is application.properties.
Second,
uh our conceptual framework code is like
we have to create a new Kafka consumer
object and this properties we need to
feed.
So, good thing is there is a
framework class consumer factory.
Okay? So, this is you can say that
interface and this is an implementation.
This is an implementation class. Okay?
What it does is it task is to create an
object of Kafka consumer. So,
what it will do is that it will make use
of your application.properties,
it will convert it to this properties,
and then
it can create the new Kafka consumer
object and feed this property map to it.
Okay? And we don't have to write this.
Already framework provide this. This
class is already framework provide this.
So, this classes has the capability to
create an object of Kafka consumer.
Done.
This is also handled.
Now, here if you see,
consumer, which topic it need to listen
to.
Okay?
Where we have to provide it? Into the
Kafka listener. So, we have to provide a
Kafka listener. This is we have to
write. This is we have to provide. So,
one we have to provide is
application.properties, second is we
have to provide is Kafka listener. So,
in the Kafka listener, at the rate Kafka
listener,
topic equals to this. So, this is this
piece of code we have to tell.
Subscribe.
This information come from this Kafka
listener. Okay?
Now, also
if you receive that in the for loop,
let's say 50 records come for this 50
record one by one, this business logic
will run, right? This business logic is
also
this one.
So, the Kafka listener is written on top
of a method.
So, whatever the method is nothing but
your business logic.
So, for each event one by one, your
business logic means this method will
get invoked.
So, this is also handle this business
logic.
Now, here if you see the rest of the
code, this framework code you can say
that
polling, auto commit, this for loop
iteration, this manual commit and all,
this all is present into Kafka listener
container.
Okay? And again, the framework provide
this. We don't have to write.
So, all we have to write is this
application.properties
and this Kafka listener. Only these two
things. Rest is everything is provided.
So,
at this point of time, we know that,
okay,
even though we are writing only
application.properties, Kafka listener,
there are so many things framework is
doing.
Something is handled by consumer
factory, something is handled by Kafka
listener,
and something is by listener, Kafka
listener and all.
But, what is the flow now?
Okay? Let's again join some
like connect the dots.
Now, here I'm showing you the flow.
Now, with this
all the dots will get connected.
Now, you start your Spring Boot
application.
So, when you start the Spring Boot
application in the pom.xml,
you have provided a spring-kafka.
Right?
So,
auto configuration, Kafka auto
configuration will start. It will get
triggered.
Okay? Based on the spring-kafka on the
class path, this configuration will
trigger. What it will do?
It will create a bean, or you can say
that object of consumer factory. First
thing, it will create an bean of it.
It will not create an object of consumer
factory. It will create an object of
consumer factory first.
Because
this is an interface, this is an
implementation. So, ultimately, it will
create an object of let's say default
Kafka consumer factory. Because once you
have a bean for this, then only you
would be use it to create an object of
Kafka consumer, right? So, first thing
is you have to have a bean of this.
So, first thing, when you start an
application, based on the dependency,
Kafka auto configuration will start, and
it will create a bean of your consumer
factory. That is done.
Okay?
The second is it will create a bean of
concurrent Kafka listener container
factory. If you see,
there is something called Kafka listener
container. Where I showed you it has all
this code.
All this try loop, the polling where it
does, right?
Uh auto commit, manual commit, for loop,
okay? So, this all present inside into
Kafka listener container.
But you can say that it is like a
factory of it.
Concurrent Kafka listener container
factory.
So, a bean is created for this also, and
this factory
object is, you can say that, wrapped
inside it. Okay? So, this holds this
holds the reference of consumer factory.
So, at the step one, when you start a
Spring Boot application,
object is created for consumer factory,
and this object is is stored inside into
concurrent Kafka listener container
factory. So, its bean is also created.
It's been is also created.
Now,
we have to add \at} \rate} enable Kafka.
This in all your application.
It is not mandatory. Even if you don't
add it, a Spring Boot automatically adds
it. If you are not using a Spring Boot,
let's say, then you have to add in your
application that \at} \rate} enable
Kafka annotation. Because without this,
it will not listen to this
annotation \at} \rate} Kafka listener.
Okay?
So,
if you see
in our Kafka consumer application, I
have not added. But,
internally,
internally, a Spring Boot might be
adding it. But, we don't have to add it.
A Spring Boot automatically add it for
us.
But, what happens after this is like
when this is added, which a Spring Boot
automatically adds, because we have a
Spring Kafka
dependency in palm, what it will do is
it will create a bean of this Kafka
listener annotation bean post processor.
What this task is to is it is scan Kafka
listeners. It is scanning this. It is
scan this.
Okay?
Once it is scan this, now let's say it
found one.
For each Kafka listener, for each Kafka
listener, it will ask concurrent Kafka
listener container factory, "Hey, create
an object of Kafka listener fact
container bean. Create and this object.
Create this object."
Okay?
So, [snorts] again,
when this annotation is added, which is
automatically added,
a post processor, you can say that work
is start.
What it does it it scan your repo and
look for Kafka listener annotation.
Now, let's say it found two.
So, what it will do is it will ask
concurrent Kafka listener container
factory, this one, the bean which is
already created. It will ask, "Hey,
I got two Kafka listener.
Create two
Kafka listener container object.
Kafka listener container object one,
Kafka listener container object two.
Each for
this Kafka listener.
Okay? Now, here if you see, this Kafka
listener container
internally
make
create Kafka consumer object from the
consumer factory.
Okay?
Because this object already has the
reference of this consumer factory.
And this consumer factory is ultimately
used to create an object of Kafka
consumer.
Okay? So, now when you are creating an
object of Kafka listener container, and
Kafka listener container is like you can
say that it's a template.
While true, it do the polling, it do
auto commit. Okay?
Then it will have iterate over each
record, and it invoke your business
logic, everything. So, this is the main
thing.
So, when we are creating an object of it
for each Kafka listener. So, now let's
say
currently I have this one Kafka listener
only. So, one object would be created
for
Kafka listener container. So, what it
will do is it will need a
you can say that consumer object. So, it
will make use of
concurrent Kafka listener factory. What
it will do is it already has
this consumer factory object, right? It
will create an object of this. So, means
each Kafka listener container
each Kafka listener container has one
Kafka
consumer.
One Kafka consumer. So, in a Spring
Boot, if you have two Kafka listener,
two Kafka listener means
you have two Kafka listener container,
and two Kafka listener container means
you have two consumer.
Okay?
Got it?
So, means you have two
consumer in a group.
Which topic they might be listening that
it is defined here in the Kafka listener
itself. But, they belongs to one group.
Okay?
So, now here in the Kafka listener
container,
so you need a consumer object. Yes, it
would be created by the concurrent one
because it has the reference of consumer
factory.
Then this
code logic is there, then business
logic. Like which business logic it has
to invoke?
So, it has already read the Kafka
listener, right? For each Kafka
listener. So,
this consumer will invoke this business
logic.
So, you have a second Kafka listener.
Second Kafka listener means second
object of Kafka listener container, and
that will invoke
its business logic.
Okay? That's why each Kafka listener,
again very important, in the Spring
Boot, each Kafka listener,
if you have 10 Kafka listener,
10 Kafka listener container will get
created, and each Kafka listener creator
has one consumer.
Got it?
The
The flow is clear?
Okay? So, it is scan the Kafka listener.
Let's say it got one.
What it will do is it will
create a Kafka listener container out of
it.
And So it contain
create the Kafka listener container, it
now has all the information what
business logic I have to add. Okay?
Consumer it will create. It will create
one consumer, which business I have to
invoke. Every information it has, what
topic I
uh it it has to listen. It has
everything.
So container it would be able to create
successfully.
And after that you have poll loop start.
It continuously iterate over in the
while loop itself. Continuously while
while.
So this part is clear, right? I know
that it can be confusing. Like if you
just go with high level that it's
setting up a consumer is no hard deal.
But understanding it like what
internally it might be doing
and what's the flow actually.
So
this is the actual Spring Boot flow
in my view
internally happens.
But again,
there is so many questions in this flow,
which I will cover in the next part.
Let's say
I'm just asking in this flow itself if I
go.
Okay?
Hey,
group coordinator assign the partition.
What are the different algorithms? Like
why why consumer got partition zero?
How? What are the different ways
of deciding this like which consumer get
which partition?
This is one question doubt.
What if there is no event and we know
that it is continuously doing while true
while true. Okay?
So what if there is no event? Is there
is like a hold on period like okay if
there is no event our consumer will wait
for some time. So there are like so many
questions and I will cover into the next
part, but I hope that
you try to implement by your hand. You
able to set up set cluster, producer,
consumer. At least this one happy flow
we would be able to run and it just not
like we done it. We You be able to
understand this flow internally also
like what might be happening.
Any doubt? Let me know. We can discuss
further into the comment section. Bye.